About a year and a half ago,
نحو سنة ونصف مضت
Stephen Lawler, who also gave a talk
ستيفن لولر الذي تحدث أيضا
here at TED in 2007 on Virtual Earth,
هنا في تيد في عام 2007 عن الأرض الافتراضية
brought me over to become the architect of Bing Maps,
شجعني على أن أصبح مهندسا في خرائط بينج،
which is Microsoft's online-mapping effort.
التي تعتبر جهدا من مايكروسوفت لرسم الخرائط على الإنترنت.
In the past two and a half, we've been very hard at work
في العامين والنصف الماضيين، كنا نعمل بجهد كبير
on redefining the way maps work online.
على إعادة تعريف طريقة عمل الخرائط غلى الإنترنت.
And we really are seeing this in very different terms
ونحن بالفعل نرى ذلك من خلال شروط مختلفة جدا
from the kind of mapping and direction site
عن هذا النوع من موقع الخرائط والاتجاهات
that one is used to.
التي اعتاد عليها الناس.
So, the first thing that you might notice about the mapping site
لذا، فإن أول شيء قد تلاحظه عن موقع الخرائط،
is just the fluidity of the zooming and the panning,
هو سهولة التكبير والدوران،
which, if you're familiar at all with Seadragon,
التي، إذا كنت على دراية بسيدراجون،
that's where it comes from.
فهي تأتي من هناك.
Mapping is, of course,
رسم الخرائط هو، بطبيعة الحال،
not just about cartography,
ليس فقط عبارة عن رسم خرائط،
it's also about imagery.
إنه أيضا عبارة عن التصوير.
So, as we zoom-in beyond a certain level
لذلك، فيما نحن نقوم بالتكبير فوق مستوى معين
this resolves into a kind of Sim City-like
يأخذنا إلى نوع من مثل سيم سيتي
virtual view at 45 degrees.
في عرض افتراضي على 45 درجة.
This can be viewed from any of the cardinal directions
ويمكن مشاهدتها من أي اتجاه من الاتجاهات الأساسية
to show you the 3D structure of the city, all the facades.
لتظهر لك الهيكل الثلاثي الأبعاد للمدينة، وجميع الواجهات.
Now, we see this space, this three-dimensional environment,
الآن، نحن نرى هذه المنطقة، وهذه البيئة الثلاثية الأبعاد
as being a canvas on which
التي تبدو كلوحة
all sorts of applications can play out,
تجرى عليها جميع أنواع التطبيقات.
and map's directions are really just one of them.
ووجهات الخريطة هي في الواقع واحدة منها فقط.
If you click on this, you'll see
إذا نقرت على هذا فسترى
some of the ones that we've put out, just in the past couple of months
بعضا من تلك التي عرضناها، في الشهرين الماضيين فقط،
since we've launched.
منذ انطلاقنا.
So, for example, a couple of days after the disaster in Haiti,
هكذا، على سبيل المثال، بعد يومين من وقوع الكارثة في هايتي،
we had an earthquake map that showed
كان لدينا خريطة الزلزال الذي أظهر
before and after pictures from the sky.
صور ما قبل وبعد الزلزال مأخوذة من السماء.
This wonderful one which I don't have time to show you
هذا التطبيق الرائع الذي ليس لدي الوقت لأريكم إياه
is taking hyper-local blogs in real time
يأخذ مدونات محلية نشطة في الوقت الحقيقي
and mapping those stories, those entries
ويرسم خرائط تلك القصص، تلك الإدخالات
to the places that are referred to on the blogs.
إلى الأماكن التي يشار إليها في المدونات.
It's wonderful.
إنه رائع.
But I'm going to show you some more candy sort of stuff.
ولكنني سأريكم بعض الأمور الأكثر إمتاعا.
So, we see the imagery, of course,
هكذا، نحن نرى التصوير، بطبيعة الحال،
not stopping at the sky.
لا يتوقف في السماء.
These little green bubbles represent
هذه الفقاقيع الصغيرة الخضراء تمثل
photosynths that users have made.
التعليمات (photosynths) التي وضعها المستخدمون.
I'm not going to dive into them either, but photosynths are integrated into the map.
لن أخوض في تعريفها أيضا، ولكن photosynths مدمجة في الخريطة.
Everything that's cased in blue
كل ما هو مغطى بالأزرق
is an area where we've taken imagery on the ground as well.
هو أحد المناطق التي قمنا بأخذ صور لها على أرض الواقع أيضا.
And so, when you fly down --
وهكذا، عندما تهبط
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you. When you fly down to the ground,
شكرا. عندما تهبط إلى لأرض،
and you see this kind of panoramic imagery,
وترى هذا النوع من التصوير البانورامي،
the first thing that you might notice is that it's not just a picture,
الشيء الأول الذي قد تلاحظ أنه ليس مجرد صورة،
there's just as much three-dimensional understanding of this environment
هناك تقدير ثلاثي الأبعاد في هذه البيئة
as there is of the three-dimensional city from above,
يعادل التقدير الثلاثي الأبعاد للمدينة من الأعلى،
so if I click on something to get a closer view of it,
لذا لو نقرت على شيء للحصول على عرض أقرب من ذلك،
then, the fact that that transition looks as it does,
من ثم، حقيقة أن هذا التحول يبدو كما هو في الواقع،
is a function of all of that geometry,
هو وظيفة جميع تلك الهندسات،
all of that 3D understanding behind this model.
جميع تلك التقديرات الثلاثية الأبعاد وراء هذا النموذج.
Now, I'll show you a fun app
الآن، سأريكم تطبيقا ممتعا
that -- we've been working on a collaboration with our friends at Flickr.
اننا نعمل على التعاون مع أصدقائنا في فلكر.
This takes Flickr, georegistered imagery
هذا التطبيق يأخذ تصوير هندسي مسجل من فلكر
and uses photosynth-like processes
ويستخدم عمليات شبيهة ب photosynth
to connect that imagery to our imagery, so --
لربط ذلك التصوير بالتصوير الخاص بنا، لذلك --
I'm not sure if that's the one I actually meant to pull up, but --
لست متأكدا اذا كان هذا الذي كنت اعني عرضه، ولكن --
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But notice -- this is, of course, a popular tourist site,
لكن لاحظ -- وهذا هو، بطبيعة الحال، موقع سياحي شهير،
and there are lots of photos around here,
وهناك الكثير من الصور من حولنا هنا،
and these photos are all taken at different times.
وقد التقطت جميع هذه الصور في أوقات مختلفة.
So this one was taken around five.
هذه الصورة التقطت حوالي الساعة الخامسة.
So that's the Flickr photo,
هذه صورة فلكر(Flickr)،
that's our imagery.
وهذا تصويرنا.
So you really see how this kind of crowd-sourced imagery
لذا انتم بالفعل ترون كيف يتم دمج ذلك النوع من الصور التي التقطها الناس
is integrating, in a very deep way, into the map itself.
بطريقة عميقة جدا، في الخريطة نفسها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
There are several reasons why this is interesting
هناك عدة أسباب تجعله مثيرا للاهتمام
and one of them, of course, is time travel.
واحد منها، بالطبع، هو الوقت الذي يستغرقه السفر.
And I'm not going to show you some of the wonderful historic imagery in here,
ولن أريكم بعضا من التصوير التاريخي الرائع هنا،
but there are some with horses and carriages and so on as well.
ولكن هناك بعض من صور الخيول والعربات كذلك.
But what's cool about this is that, not only is it augmenting
ولكن ما هو رائع حول هذا التطبيق هو أنه، لا يعمل فقط على تضخيم
this visual representation of the world
هذا التمثيل البصري للعالم
with things that are coming in from users,
بالأشياء التي تأتي من المستخدمين،
but it also is the foundation for augmented reality,
لكنه أيضا هو الأساس لتضخيم الواقع،
and that's something that I'll be showing you more of in just a moment.
الذي سأريكم المزيد منه في لحظات.
Now I just made a transition indoors. That's also interesting.
لقد انتقلت الآن إلى الداخل. وهذا أيضا مثير للاهتمام.
OK, notice there's now a roof above us.
حسنا، لاحظوا أنه يوجد سقف فوقنا.
We're inside the Pike Place Market.
نحن داخل سوق Pike Place.
And this is something that we're able to do with a backpack camera,
وهذا شيء نستطيع القيام به باستعمال الكاميرا المحمولة،
so, we're now not only imaging in the street
إذا، نحن لا نصور في الشارع فقط
with this camera on tops of cars,
مع هذه الكاميرا على أسطح السيارات،
but we're also imaging inside.
ولكننا أيضا نصور في الداخل.
And from here, we're able to do the same sorts of registration,
ومن هنا، نستطيع القيام بنفس النوع من التسجيل،
not only of still images, but also of video.
ليس فقط من الصور الثابته، ولكن أيضا من الفيديو.
So this is something that we're now going to try
وهذا شيء سوف نقوم بتجربته الآن
for the first time, live,
لأول مرة، في بث حي
and this is really, truly, very frightening.
وهذا حقا، حقا، مخيف للغاية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
OK.
حسنا.
(Ringing)
(رنين)
All right, guys, are you there?
حسنا، يا رفاق، هل أنتم هناك؟
(Noise)
(إزعاج)
All right. I'm hitting it. I'm punching play.
حسنا، سأضغط الآن، سأضغط زر التشغيل.
I'm live. All right. There we go.
أنا في بث حي. حسنا. ها نحن هناك.
So, these are our friends in Pike Place Market, the lab.
اذا، هؤلاء هم أصدقاؤنا في سوق Pike Place، المعمل
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So they're broadcasting this live.
وهم يبثون لنا مباشرة.
OK, George, can you pan back over to the corner market?
حسنا، جورج، هل يمكنك الدوران للخلف إلى زاوية السوق؟
Because I want to show points of interest.
لأنني أريد ان تظهر النقاط المثيرة للاهتمام.
No, no. The other way.
لا، لا. الجهة الأخرى.
Yeah, yeah, back to the corner, back to the corner.
نعم، نعم. ارجع إلى الزاوية. ارجع إلى الزاوية.
I don't want to see you guys yet.
لا أريد أن أراكم يا رفاق بعد.
OK, OK, back to the corner, back to the corner, back to the corner.
حسنا. حسنا. ارجع إلى الخلف. ارجع إلى الخلف. ارجع إلى الخلف.
OK, never mind.
حسنا. لا تقلق.
What I wanted to show you was these points of interest
ما أردت أن أبين لكم كانت هذه النقاط المثيرة للاهتمام
over here on top of the image
من هنا على أعلى الصورة
because what that gives you a sense of is the way,
لأن الشعور الذي يمنحكم إياه هو الطريقة،
if you're actually on the spot,
اذا كنت متواجدا فعلا في المكان ...
you can think about this --
يمكنك التفكير في هذا --
this is taking a step in addition to augmented reality.
هو اتخاذ خطوة بالإضافة إلى تضخيم الواقع.
What the hell are you guys -- oh, sorry.
ماذا يا رفاق -- أوه ، آسف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
We're doing two different --
نحن نعمل على شيئين مختلفين ...
OK, I'm hanging up now.
حسنا، سأغلق الخط الآن.
We're doing two different things here.
نحن نعمل على شيئين مختلفين هنا.
One of them is to take that real ...
أحدهم هو أن نأخذ هذا ...
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
All right, let me just take a moment and thank the team.
حسنا، اسمحوا لي أن أتوقف لحظة لأشكر فريق العمل.
They've done a fantastic job of pulling this together.
لقد قاموا بعمل رائع.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
I'm going to abandon them now and walk back outside.
سوف أتخلى عنهم الآن وأعود للخارج.
And while I walk outside, I'll just mention that
وبينما أمشي خارجا، سأشير إلى
here we're using this for telepresence,
هنا، نستخدم خاصية التواجد عن بُعد (telepresence)،
but you can equally well use this
ولكن يمكنكم استخدامه بشكل مواز
on the spot, for augmented reality.
على الفور، في تضخيم الواقع.
When you use it on the spot, it means that
عند استخدامه على الفور، هذا يعني أنكم
you're able to bring all of that metadata
قادرون على إظهار كل ذلك التعريف
and information about the world to you.
وتلك المعلومات حول العالم لكم.
So here, we're taking the extra step of also broadcasting it.
وهنا، إننا نتخذ الخطوة الإضافية في بثه أيضا.
That was being broadcast, by the way, on a 4G network
التي نشاهدها، بالمناسبة، على شبكة 4G
from the market.
من السوق.
All right, and now there's one last TED talk
حسنا، هناك محاضرة أخيرة من تيد
that Microsoft has given in the past several years.
قدمتها مايكروسوفت في السنوات القليلة الماضية.
And that's Curtis Wong, WorldWide Telescope.
وألقى المحاضرة كيرتس وونغ، وورلد وايد تليسكوب.
So, we're going to head over to the dumpsters,
والآن نتجه إلى
where it's traditional, after a long day at the market,
حيث أنه تقليدي، بعد يوم طويل في السوق،
to go out for a break, but also stare up at the sky.
الخروج في فسحة، ولكن أيضا التحديق في السماء
This is the integration
وهذا هو الدمج
of WorldWide Telescope into our maps.
لوورلد وايد تليسكوب في خرائطنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This is the current -- thank you --
هذا هو -- شكرا --
this is the current time. If we scrub the time,
هذا هو الوقت الحالي، ولكن إذا حركنا الوقت،
then we can see how the sky will look at different times,
عندها يمكننا أن نرى السماء مختلفة باختلاف الوقت،
and we can get all of this very detailed
ويمكننا الحصول على كل هذه المعلومات
information about different times, different dates:
المفصلة عن اوقات وتواريخ مختلفة.
Let's move the moon a little higher in the sky,
دعونا ننقل القمر أعلى قليلا في السماء،
maybe change the date.
ربما نغير التاريخ.
I would like to kind of zoom in on the moon.
أود تكبير القمر نوعا ما.
So, this is an astronomically complete
هذا هو تمثيل فلكي
representation of the sky
كامل للسماء
integrated right into the Earth.
مدمج مع الأرض.
All right now, I've overrun my time,
حسنا الآن، لقد انتهى وقتي،
so I've got to stop.
لذا علي التوقف.
Thank you all very much.
أشكركم جميعا جزيل الشكر.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)